Guide to the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation papers
1940-1982
MS 1139
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
86
(136 cartons, 134 film cans)
The papers consist of raw data, videotapes, and films from two of Margaret Mahler's studies: the Natural History of Symbiotic Child Psychosis and the Normal Separation-Individuation studies.
Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation
Conditions Governing Access
Written permission to access or make reproductions from the collection is required from the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation until January 1, 2058, after which the collection is open to research without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation, 1980, 1985. Gift of William Singletary, 1997.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. Natural History of Symbiotic Child Psychosis, 1957-1965. II. Normal Separation-Individuation Studies, 1962-1977. III. Videotapes, 1962-. IV. Films, 1940s-1982.
Scope and Contents
The Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation papers contain the research documents, raw and processed data, videotapes and films stemming from Mahler's research studies of tics in children, on childhood psychosis and the studies of normal child development. The material dates from 1955-1977. In the 1940s Mahler conducted research studying tics in children at the New York State Psychiatric Institute, Children's Services Division with Dr. Jean Luke and Leo Rangell. In the 1960s an electrical fire destroyed the majority of research information pertaining to the tic studies. A limited amount of research film and publications from this study remain. The publications are located in the Margaret S. Mahler Papers (MS Group # 1138). The majority of the Foundation material stems from the studies on child psychosis which Mahler conducted with Manuel Furer in the 1950s under the title of "the natural history of symbiotic child psychosis" and of the studies of normal child development, also known as the separation-individuation studies, with Calvin Settlage, Fred Pine and Anni Bergman from 1960-1972. From these studies Mahler developed her theory of separation-individuation in which a child grows through various psychological and physical stages which enable it to recognize its independence from the mother, (individuation) and then in turn pass through the physical break from its mother, (separation). Also included in the papers are films which were created by the Foundation for teaching purposes, and in conjunction with projects sponsored by the Foundation.
The Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation deposited the material in Manuscripts and Archives from 1979-1983. Original order of the material has been maintained. The bulk of the material dates from 1960-1972 when Mahler and her co-workers were conducting the studies of normal child development. The papers are arranged in four series: I. NATURAL HISTORY OF SYMBIOTIC CHILD PSYCHOSIS, II. NORMAL SEPARATION-INDIVIDUATION STUDIES, III. VIDEOTAPES, and IV. FILMS.
Series I, NATURAL HISTORY OF SYMBIOTIC CHILD PSYCHOSIS, contains applications, observations, reports of children in the therapeutic nursery, and conference minutes, for the study of symbiotic child psychosis which Mahler conducted in the 1950s. The applications contain information about children who were accepted or rejected for the study. Observations include daily and monthly summaries of the children, reports by the social worker involved with the study concerning the mothers of the children, reports by the therapist concerning the activities of the children and their families, and reports by non-participating observers who conducted unobtrusive observations from within the nursery setting. In addition, records of treatment summaries of the children, psychiatric exams of the children and parents, and interviews of the mothers are also maintained. Material from the therapeutic nursery contains observations and reports. Conference minutes contain discussions of staff observations and suggestions for treatment of the children.
The material is arranged by type. The applications, observations and therapeutic nursery materials are arranged alphabetically by child. The conference minutes are arranged chronologically.
Series II, NORMAL SEPARATION-INDIVIDUATION STUDIES, contains applications, observations, film observations and processed data in the form of notebooks; the methodology for the studies, including forms listing the areas of observations for and the ratings of each of the children; the raw data describing the categories and ratings of the children; research conference minutes, testing schedules, and microfilm/microfiche sets of the notebooks and processed data for the studies which were conducted from 1959-1973. Materials for the "early children" who began the study in 1959 include applications containing general information, medical histories and psychological examinations of the children. In addition, group observations of the children are maintained with this material. Materials relating to the further studies of the childrens' normal development consist of notebooks containing: a) "once only" material including general birth information, early medical information, personal and family histories, physical home layouts, results of developmental tests, and letters of recommendation from attending schools; b) observations, of the children by the researchers in selected categories; c) ratings of the children in additional categories by research staff; d) reduced data of specific observations including what Mahler termed 'Ten Questions' dealing with the physical awareness of the children in the nursery, and the 'Four Topics' concerning the psychological experiences of the children; e) reactions observed by the staff relating to the separation from the mother, the sleep of the child, the introduction of a stranger to the mother-child situation, and the mirror reactions of the child; f) interim materials include observations of play sessions; g) follow-up and summaries include observations and assessments made by research staff concerning the childrens' progress from the beginning to the end of the study; and h) mothers' books include interviews of the mothers and fathers as well as observations of the parents in the nursery setting. These notebooks are copies of the originals which are still in the possession of the Mahler Foundation. There is a limited amount of duplicate material for the children. This material is maintained separately from the notebook material.
Raw data includes observations of the children in specific categories and ratings of the children by the research staff as described by the methodology created for the study. The children were observed in eighteen categories: feeding and oral behavior; toileting; motor and locomotor activity; sleep; body self awareness as reaction to anatomical sex differences; reaction to strangers; imitation, play and fantasy; speech and communication; aggression; reaction to pain and frustration; mother; mother-child interaction; differences between home and Masters Children's Center; important events in family; information about father; typical and exaggerated behavior; siblings and contemporaries; summary.
Reduced data includes observations by the research staff documenting the physical and psychological experiences of the child in the nursery setting. Mahler and her co-workers developed a set of "Ten Questions" and "Four Topics" which include observations on aggression & psychosexual development, mood, mood by subphases, perceptions-cognitive-language development, object relations, brief statements, key statements, checking back reactions, early feeding & weaning, ego functions, development of locomotion, and separation reactions.
Film observations contain notes from the researchers and non-participant observers who observed specific reactions in the children including: checking back reactions, early fantasy activity, early feeding & weaning activity, ego functions, development of locomotor activity, and separation reactions. In addition, the notes contain selected film sequences of the children.
Descriptions of the methodology and rationale for the normal development studies are contained in the notes, early rating scales and procedures devised by Fred Pine. Early and later versions of the rating scales and methods for applying their use in observations are found in these files.
McDevitt Notebooks contain materials relating to the follow-up studies undertaken by John McDevitt with some of the children from the initial study. Observations contain information regarding female development and gender identity of the female children under study.
The research conference minutes contain transcripts of meetings attended by the research staff where the project and treatment of the children were discussed. The schedules document the observational and testing activity of the research staff.
The microfiche and microfilm sets of the notebooks contain duplicate raw and processed data maintained by Mahler on each of the study children. There are four microfilm/microfiche sets each containing: 1) area observations; 2) coordinated observations; 3) film notes and observations; 4) reduced data--narrative and general remarks. The observations card index contains notecards with observations of the children arranged by type of reaction.
Series III, VIDEOTAPES, contains edited versions of the research film from the Normal Separation-Individuation studies. These include videotapes of individual children, and of children in specific subphases of development. The tapes include longitudinal studies, as well as condensed versions.
Series IV, FILMS, contains the original and copy observational film recorded during Mahler's studies of tics in children, childhood psychosis, and of normal childhood development. The tic studies films include footage of Mahler's child patients as well as footage of patients of her co-worker Dr. Jean Luke. The subjects in this study range from six to twenty-five years in age. Tic studies observations are filmed on 16mm film. The natural history of symbiotic child psychosis film contains observations of the children from this study from the spring of 1960 to the spring of 1963. Film from the normal separation-individuation studies contains original, copy and longitudinal prints filmed at the Masters Children's Center by Mahler and her co-workers. In addition to the positive prints of the longitudinal film, duplicate negative of the film has also been maintained. The film is arranged by name of child or pairs of children and is black and white 16mm film. In addition to the studies films, 36 reels of teaching and project films are located at the end of this series.
Biographical / Historical
In 1972 the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Fund was formed with matching funds from the Menil Foundation Inc., of Houston, Texas. The purpose of the Fund was to ensure the preservation of Mahler's research through the maintenance of her research archives, and to provide funding for continued research in the areas of child development and child psychosis.
The Mahler archive at the time consisted of research films, documents, raw and processed data, manuscripts and publications stemming from Mahler's studies of tics in children, on childhood psychosis, and the studies of normal child development. The Fund supported the physical preservation, reproduction and cataloging of the films and research documentation. In addition, the Fund provided money for Mahler to continue to write about her research, to fund the then current and follow-up studies of normal child development, and to provide funding for any future studies stemming from Mahler's work.
The Fund also supported the promotion of research and scientific publication in the fields of child development and analysis by Mahler and others through available means and the establishment of the Margaret S. Mahler Literature Prize, and publication by the Fund of scientific papers, monographs and/or books growing out of research supported by the Fund. The Fund also sponsored projects by individuals and groups that focused on child development and child analysis. Additionally, the Fund co-sponsored the Margaret S. Mahler Child Development Symposium Series in collaboration with the Medical College of Pennsylvania, Department of Psychiatry and the Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute.
In 1976, the Fund became independent of the Menil Foundation and was renamed the Margaret S. Mahler Psychiatric Research Foundation, with its primary purposes remaining the same as those of its predecessor. The Foundation continues the work begun by Margaret S. Mahler.
- Natural History of Symbiotic Child Psychosis, 1957-1965; Series I; 4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged by type of material and contains applications, observations, therapeutic nursery files and staff conference minutes for the study of the natural history of symbiotic child psychosis. Applications are arranged alphabetically by last name of child. Observations of the children are arranged alphabetically by first name. Therapeutic nursery files are arranged alphabetically by last name of the child. Staff Conference minutes are arranged chronologically.
  - Applications
    - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rejected
      - A-H, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
      - J-N, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
      - R-St, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
      - V-Z, undated (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    - A., Bruce, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - B., Bruce, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - B., Helane, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - B., David, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - B., Kevin, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - C., Michael, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - C., Mitchell, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - E., Mark, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - E., Hadassah, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - E., Harriet, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - F., Faith, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - F., Christopher, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - F., Stephen, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - G., Noah, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - G., Howard, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - H., George, undated (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
    - H., David, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - J., Hulan, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - J., Margaret, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - K., Philip, undated (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
    - K., Maxwell, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - M., Denise, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - M., David, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - M., Henry, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - P., Michael, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - S., Isser, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - S., Laura, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - T., Michael, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - W., Michele, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Observations
    - Iris A.
      - Daily summaries, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 52-53)
      - Monthly summaries, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Social worker's reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 55-57)
      - Social worker's reports, 1963, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 59-60)
      - Therapist's reports, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 61-64)
      - Non-participating observations, 1962, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
      - Treatment summary, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Mrs. A.-Interviews, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Mrs. A.-Psychological exams, 1960, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Psychiatric exam, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Film notes, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Bruce B.
      - Intake study, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - Daily summaries, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - History and summary, 1965, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - Monthly summaries, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Non-participating observations, 1962, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Social worker's reports, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 77-78)
      - Social worker's reports, 1963, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - Mrs. B.-Psychological reports, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 80)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Therapist's reports, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 82-87)
    - Victoria F.
      - Intake study, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 88-89)
      - Monthly summaries, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Non-participating observations, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 91)
      - Social worker's reports, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 92)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 93-94)
      - Supervisor's notes, 1961, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 95)
      - Therapist's reports, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 96)
      - Supervisor's reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Scott P.
      - Monthly summaries, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - Non-participating observations, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - Intake study, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - Social worker, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - Therapist's reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Johnny G.
      - Intake study, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 104)
      - Monthly summaries, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 105)
      - Non-participating observations, 1962, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 106)
      - Social worker's reports, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 107-109)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 110-112)
      - Supervisory reports, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 113-117)
      - Therapist's reports, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 118)
      - Therapist's reports, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 119-121)
      - Summary reports, undated (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - Alan M.
      - Intake study, 1960, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 123)
      - Non-participating observations, 1961, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 124)
      - Social worker's reports, 1961, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 125-126)
      - Supervisor's conferences and reports, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 127)
      - Therapists's reports, 1961, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - David A.
      - Intake study, undated (Box 7, Folder 129)
      - Non-participating observations, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 130)
      - Monthly summaries, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 131)
      - Therapist's reports, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 132)
      - Mrs. A.-Interviews, 1959, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - Abby F.
      - Intake study, 1959, 1963, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 134)
      - Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 135)
      - Non-participating observations, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 136)
      - Social worker's observations, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 137)
      - Supervisor's conferences, 1960, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 138)
      - Therapist's reports, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 139-140)
    - Mitchell N.
      - Non-participating observations, 1960-1963 (Box 8, Folder 141)
      - Social worker's reports, 1960-1963 (Box 8, Folder 142-145)
      - Therapist's reports, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 146)
      - Daily summaries, 1961, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 147)
      - Therapist's reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 148)
      - Teaching sessions, 1962, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 149)
      - Tutoring reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 150)
      - Mrs. N.-Interview, 1961, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 151)
      - Notes, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - Film Discussion, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Therapeutic Nursery
    - Kim B.
      - Intake study, 1958, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 154)
      - Referral and summary reports, 1959, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 155)
      - Social worker's reports, 1958, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 156)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 157)
      - Teacher's reports, 1958-1960 (Box 9, Folder 158)
    - Peter B.
      - Intake study, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 159)
      - Social worker's reports, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 160)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 161)
      - Teacher's reports, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Robert C.
      - Intake study, undated (Box 9, Folder 163)
      - Non-participating observations, 1959, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 164)
      - Social worker's reports, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 165)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 166)
      - Therapist's reports, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Ranaan G.
      - Intake study, 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 168)
      - Referral and summary reports, 1957, 1959, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 169)
      - Social worker's reports, 1957-1959 (Box 9, Folder 170)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1958, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 171)
      - Teacher's reports, 1958, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 172)
      - Drawings, undated (Box 10, Folder 173)
    - Margaret J.
      - Intake study, 1959, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 174)
      - Social worker's reports, 1958, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 175)
      - Supervisory conference, 1958, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 176)
      - Treatment summary, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 177)
      - Teacher's reports, 1958, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 178)
    - Susan P.
      - Intake study, 1957-1959, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 179)
      - Referrals and summary reports, 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 180)
      - Non-participating observations, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 181)
      - Social worker's reports, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 182)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 183)
      - Teacher's reports, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 184)
      - Drawings, undated (Box 10, Folder 185)
    - Danny R.
      - Intake study, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 186)
      - Drawings, undated (Box 10, Folder 187)
      - Referral reports, 1960-1962, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 188)
      - Social worker's reports, 1958-1960 (Box 10, Folder 189)
      - Teacher's reports, 1959, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 190)
    - Norman R.
      - Intake study, 1960, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 191)
      - Non-participating observations, 1961 (Box 10, Folder 192)
      - Social worker's reports, 1960, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 193)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 194)
      - Teacher's reports, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 195)
      - Therapist's reports, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - Robert S.
      - Intake study, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 197)
      - Treatment summary, 1963, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 198)
      - Social worker's reports, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 199-200)
      - Teacher's reports, 1958-1960 (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - Avra W.
      - Intake study, 1957-1959 (Box 11, Folder 202)
      - Social worker's reports, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 203)
      - Supervisory conferences, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 204)
      - Teacher's reports, 1958, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 205)
  - Staff Conference Minutes
    - General, 1959-1964 (Box 11, Folder 206-210)
- Normal Separation-Individuation Studies, 1959-1977; Series II; 54.5 linear feet (67 boxes)